"Spontaneous Regression
of Cancer with Fasting"
In 2015, a remarkable case report
was published in which a woman
with Stage 3 follicular lymphoma
underwent a medically supervised,
21-day water-only fast, after which
her enlarged lymph nodes
were substantially reduced in size.
The patient then remained
on a whole food, plant-based diet,
and at 6- and 9-month follow-up
visits she remained asymptomatic.
In 2018, her 3-year
follow-up was published.
Remarkably, she appeared
to remain cancer-free,
confirmed by CT and PET scans.
Her cancer appeared to have been
knocked down and out.
The initial regression has
persisted for the three years
with no additional intervention
other than the dietary change.
Could it have just
been a coincidence?
Sure, but the initial regression
directly coincided
with the timing of her water-only fast,
suggesting a causal relationship,
and there are biological mechanisms
by which fasting may potentiate
tumor regression, such as
decreasing levels of IGF-1.
The term "spontaneous regression"
of cancer is a misnomer.
I mean, obviously there was
something that caused the regression,
whether or not we know what it is.
Presumably the immune
system plays a role.
The fact that you can get
a marked increase in cancer rates
when you're immunosuppressed
suggests that cancers are popping up
all the time, but your immune system
is normally able to keep them at bay.
There was an example, for instance,
of a regression after a transfusion
of blood from a patient
who had previously sustained
a spontaneous regression.
Or cases of patients
who had been free of metastases
for 15 or 20 years, only to develop
rapidly fatal metastases after
some type of stress or shock
that apparently sharply
reduced their resistance.
For most cancers, spontaneous
regression is exceedingly rare,
but lymphoma is an exception.
Of 140 cases of nodular lymphoma --
which is what they used
to call follicular lymphoma --
there were 18 cases of at least partial
and 6 cases of complete regression.
So like 1 in 25 cases
just go away on their own.
So when you have
follicular lymphoma cases
in which tumors shrink
after any kind of treatment --
in this case after some
herbal supplement --
you always have to ask:
is this cause-and-effect
or just coincidence?
Elevated natural killing activity may
be one of the possible mechanisms
responsible for spontaneous
regression of malignant lymphoma.
Natural killer cells may be part
of our first line of defense
against cancer by
destroying tumor cells.
And if you compare
the natural killer cell activity
of those with malignant lymphoma
that spontaneously regressed
versus those whose cancer didn't,
or a control group,
the spontaneous regression group
do seem to be on the high end.
How do we increase
natural killer cell activity?
Exercise can do it,
unless, apparently,
you're eating a high-fat diet.
Those randomized to undergo
an exercise training program
on a high-fat diet actually
suffered a decline
in natural killer cell activity,
suggesting training on a high-fat diet
is detrimental to the immune system.
Eating lots of contaminated fatty fish
may also adversely
affect NK cell levels.
But put people on a low-fat diet,
and you can dramatically increase
natural killer cell activity within
a matter of months by about 50%,
suggesting that dietary fat might
increase the formation of cancer
by depressing the tumor surveillance
capacity of the immune system.
The bottom line in terms of fasting
is that, at present, long-term fasting
in cancer treatment is supported
only by some case reports,
so more research is
desperately needed.
Sadly, there is no
current clinical research
evaluating the effects of water-only
fasting and a whole food,
plant-based diet on follicular
lymphoma in humans.
Long-term fasting is
certainly not without risk.
In this case, a guy opted
to try a 60-day fast
instead of chemotherapy
for non-Hodgkin lymphoma,
ending up hospitalized
in a coma and respiratory failure
because of Wernicke encephalopathy,
a life-threatening
neurological emergency
caused by thiamine deficiency.
But starting on a healthier diet
seems like a win-win no-brainer.
Just putting people on a plant-based,
whole food, you know,
sugar-oil-salt-free diet,
with or without fasting,
is sometimes sufficient to induce
an intense healing response.